A Guide to the Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Correspondence FA834
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Correspondence
1913-1951
Rockefeller Archive Center
Rockefeller University
Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
FA834
5 Box(es)
5 boxes.
File Plan note
Former Classification: I 425-2
Physical Characteristics and Technical Requirements
Materials requiring specialized equipment for access (film, audio, video, slides) may be restricted from scholarly research dependent on availability of the applicable equipment.
Brittle or damaged items, or materials otherwise in need of preservation care, may be restricted from scholarly research at the discretion of the RAC Head of Archival Services/RAC Head of Reference.
Arrangement
Correspondence in chronological order and by subject.
Scope and Contents
Collection of materials dealing with acquisition, building and development, decision to consolidate New York and Princeton Departments, inventories, appraisals, and sale.
Other Finding Aids
FA835 Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Subject Files.
FA968 Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Carl TenBroeck papers.
FA969 Rockefeller University records, Department of Animal and Plant Pathology, Princeton, NJ, Publications.
Conditions Governing Access note
This collection is open for scholarly research, with select materials restricted as noted.
Due to the oversize nature and potentially brittle condition of some of this material, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
Plant diseases; Medicine, Preventive; Diseases; Pathology; Biology -- Research; Cell and biomolecular sciences; Life sciences; Animals -- Diseases; Medical technology; Technology; Medical sciences; Biochemistry; Medical education; Medical research; Rockefeller University; Rockefeller Institute for Medical Research
- Correspondence (Box 1)
  Scope and Contents note
  Between Theobald Smith, T.M. Prudden, Simon Flexner, Business Manager and staff members regarding development and administration of Department at Princeton. Included are some items of correspondence with Theobald Smith. as a member of the Board of Scientific Directors.
- Correspondence, 1915 (Box 1)
  Correspondence deals with acquisition of parcels of land, Building plans, moving, temporary use of rooms at Princeton and the hiring of various workers. Many holographs from Theobald Smith. Includes list of Books and periodicals ordered for Princeton library. Dec. 28 copy of of letter from Henry James announcing Foundation Trustees' vote to make Department of Animal Pathology independent of Hill Bequest.
- Correspondence, 1916 (Box 1)
  Between Theobald Smith, Henry James and Bursar regarding details of Building, equipment, personnel and administrative routines and the partial occupation of the new Buildings at the end of October. Includes 1916 Mar. 4 Princeton Pictorial Review with story of the new department.
- Correspondence, 1917 (Box 1)
  Dealing with corrections and changes in Building plans; Buildings for residences; schedule for serum production and care of horses used. Includes copy of letter written to Dr. Amoss regarding problems with horses used for pneumonia serum production; used particularly heavily Because of war needs; other problems with horses used for serum production. Includes minutes of 1917 conferences held in Princeton and 1917 Report of Princeton Improvement Committee.
- Correspondence, 1918 (Box 1)
  dealing with continued development of property and residences; additional personnel and serum production.
- Correspondence, 1919-1920 (Box 1)
  Much of the correspondence is with T.M. Prudden dealing with development of physical plant and staff; disposition of serum production project for commercial purposes; need of Theobald Smith for assistance with administrative details. Appointment of Ernest W. Smillie as Superintendent.
- Part of paper delivered before the National Academy of Sciences meeting held at Princeton (Box 1)
- Routine administrative matters primarily with T.M. Prudden and Business Manager, 1921-1923 (Box 2)
- 1924-1925 (Box 2)
  Some correspondence regarding cooperative experiment in testing calves with a new remedy for treating tuberculosis originating from Copenhagen. January 1924 presentation to Board "Suggestions concerning directions of growth of the Department of Animal Pathology in the near future" as written by Theobald Smith (2 copies). 1924 June 13 letter from Theobald Smith to Simon Flexner looking to 65th birthday.
- Administrative correspondence primarily with E.B. Smith dealing with hiring of new employees, some expansion of facilities and possible land purchases, 1926-1927 (Box 2)
- Some correspondence dealing with status of scientific work and the appointments of Lewis, Gowan, Stoll. Correspondence under 1929 April date indicating discussion at Executive Committee meeting of Welch suggestion that Stockard be appointed successor to Theobald Smith. 1929 April 25 extract from Minutes of Board of Scientific Directors appointing an Acting Director in absence of a suitable candidate. June handwritten letter and typed copy from Simon Flexner to Theobald Smith reporting TenBroeck's consent to become Acting Director, 1928-1929 (Box 2)
- Deeds and leases (Box 2)
  Acquisition of property at Princeton.
- Correspondence, 1914-1915 (Box 3)
  Collection of letters about hog cholera and suggestions arriving after announcement of plans for the new department. Publicity regarding the purchase of land in Princeton with correspondence on purchase and authorizations to commence building and leases on certain pieces of property and insurance matters.
- Legal steps, 1913-1946 (Box 3)
  Correspondence on necessary actions and legislation to insure that Department of Animal Pathology will have freedom for animal experimentation. Material is primarily 1913-1915 when legislation was originally enacted.
- History (Box 3)
  1910 January Report with special reference to permanent endowment when idea was to expand Institute farm at Clyde, N.J. Excerpts from Minutes listing various Resolutions 1902-1932. 1914 Mar. 6 letters from Theobald Smith on tentative plans. Early steps in establishment and budgeting. 1931 and later correspondence on Plant Pathology. Feb. 1947 report of H.S. Gasser (date and author supplied from internal evidence) suggesting a need to consolidate Princeton and New York plants to meet budgetary constrictions as requested by President of Board of Trustees. Mentioned in Minutes 1947 May 2.
- 1947-1950 (Box 3)
  Excerpts from Minutes, correspondence, studies, press releases on decision to consolidate the two departments in New York City. Includes 1947 June 16 letter from Henry James on his resignation from Board of Trustees; acceptance of Board positions by Barklie Henry. Correspondence with John H. Northrop, Richard E. Shope, Harold W. Dodds (President of Princeton) and John D. Rockefeller, Jr. on announced move; letter signed by 61 employees at Princeton requesting clarification of provisions for employees. Includes charts and figures used in arriving at provisions for terminating or transferring employees.
- Sale of property (Box 3)
  Two folders with collection of floor plans and photos (attic floor plan and plan no. 5 missing) with some material on the establishment of the James Forrestal Research Center on the property and final sale arrangements.
- Photos (Box 4)
- Maps (Box 4)
  Conditions Governing Access
  Due to the oversize nature and potentially brittle condition of this material, special arrangements may be required in order to view materials. Individual items may be restricted due to preservation concerns.
- Review article from "Microbiology in New Jersey: Origins and Developments" by Selman A. Waksman, Robert L. Starkey and Richard Donovick. Edited by Robert A. Day for American Society for Microbiology, circa 1965 p. 27-34 (Box 4)
- Farm Reports (Box 5)
- Blueprints of the Department of Plant and Animal Pathology facilities (Box 5)
- Geological survey maps of the Princeton area (Box 5)